Name

glBeginConditionalRender — start conditional rendering

C Specification

void glBeginConditionalRender( | GLuint id,
  | GLenum mode);

Parameters

id

Specifies the name of an occlusion query object whose results are used to determine if the rendering commands are discarded.

mode

Specifies how glBeginConditionalRender interprets the results of the occlusion query.

C Specification

void glEndConditionalRender( | void);

Description

Conditional rendering is started using glBeginConditionalRender and ended using glEndConditionalRender. During conditional rendering, all vertex array commands, as well as glClear and glClearBuffer have no effect if the (GL_SAMPLES_PASSED) result of the query object id is zero, or if the (GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED) result is GL_FALSE. The results of commands setting the current vertex state, such as glVertexAttrib are undefined. If the (GL_SAMPLES_PASSED) result is non-zero or if the (GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED) result is GL_TRUE, such commands are not discarded. The id parameter to glBeginConditionalRender must be the name of a query object previously returned from a call to glGenQueries. mode specifies how the results of the query object are to be interpreted. If mode is GL_QUERY_WAIT, the GL waits for the results of the query to be available and then uses the results to determine if subsequent rendering commands are discarded. If mode is GL_QUERY_NO_WAIT, the GL may choose to unconditionally execute the subsequent rendering commands without waiting for the query to complete.

If mode is GL_QUERY_BY_REGION_WAIT, the GL will also wait for occlusion query results and discard rendering commands if the result of the occlusion query is zero. If the query result is non-zero, subsequent rendering commands are executed, but the GL may discard the results of the commands for any region of the framebuffer that did not contribute to the sample count in the specified occlusion query. Any such discarding is done in an implementation-dependent manner, but the rendering command results may not be discarded for any samples that contributed to the occlusion query sample count. If mode is GL_QUERY_BY_REGION_NO_WAIT, the GL operates as in GL_QUERY_BY_REGION_WAIT, but may choose to unconditionally execute the subsequent rendering commands without waiting for the query to complete.

Notes

glBeginConditionalRender and glEndConditionalRender are available only if the GL version is 3.0 or greater.

The GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED query result is available only if the GL version is 3.3 or greater.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if id is not the name of an existing query object.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if mode is not one of the accepted tokens.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if glBeginConditionalRender is called while conditional rendering is active, or if glEndConditionalRender is called while conditional rendering is inactive.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if id is the name of a query object with a target other than GL_SAMPLES_PASSED or GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if id is the name of a query currently in progress.

See Also

glGenQueries, glDeleteQueries, glBeginQuery

Copyright

Copyright © 2009 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBeginQuery — delimit the boundaries of a query object

C Specification

void glBeginQuery(GLenum target, GLuint id);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target type of query object established between glBeginQuery and the subsequent glEndQuery. The symbolic constant must be one of GL_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_PRIMITIVES_GENERATED, GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_PRIMITIVES_WRITTEN, or GL_TIME_ELAPSED.

id

Specifies the name of a query object.

C Specification

void glEndQuery(GLenum target);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target type of query object to be concluded. The symbolic constant must be one of GL_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_PRIMITIVES_GENERATED, GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_PRIMITIVES_WRITTEN, or GL_TIME_ELAPSED.

Description

glBeginQuery and glEndQuery delimit the boundaries of a query object. query must be a name previously returned from a call to glGenQueries. If a query object with name id does not yet exist it is created with the type determined by target. target must be one of GL_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED, GL_PRIMITIVES_GENERATED, GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_PRIMITIVES_WRITTEN, or GL_TIME_ELAPSED. The behavior of the query object depends on its type and is as follows.

If target is GL_SAMPLES_PASSED, id must be an unused name, or the name of an existing occlusion query object. When glBeginQuery is executed, the query object's samples-passed counter is reset to 0. Subsequent rendering will increment the counter for every sample that passes the depth test. If the value of GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS is 0, then the samples-passed count is incremented by 1 for each fragment. If the value of GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS is 1, then the samples-passed count is incremented by the number of samples whose coverage bit is set. However, implementations, at their discression may instead increase the samples-passed count by the value of GL_SAMPLES if any sample in the fragment is covered. When glEndQuery is executed, the samples-passed counter is assigned to the query object's result value. This value can be queried by calling glGetQueryObject with pname GL_QUERY_RESULT.

If target is GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED, id must be an unused name, or the name of an existing boolean occlusion query object. When glBeginQuery is executed, the query object's samples-passed flag is reset to GL_FALSE. Subsequent rendering causes the flag to be set to GL_TRUE if any sample passes the depth test. When glEndQuery is executed, the samples-passed flag is assigned to the query object's result value. This value can be queried by calling glGetQueryObject with pname GL_QUERY_RESULT.

If target is GL_PRIMITIVES_GENERATED, id must be an unused name, or the name of an existing primitive query object previously bound to the GL_PRIMITIVES_GENERATED query binding. When glBeginQuery is executed, the query object's primitives-generated counter is reset to 0. Subsequent rendering will increment the counter once for every vertex that is emitted from the geometry shader, or from the vertex shader if no geometry shader is present. When glEndQuery is executed, the primitives-generated counter is assigned to the query object's result value. This value can be queried by calling glGetQueryObject with pname GL_QUERY_RESULT.

If target is GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_PRIMITIVES_WRITTEN, id must be an unused name, or the name of an existing primitive query object previously bound to the GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_PRIMITIVES_WRITTEN query binding. When glBeginQuery is executed, the query object's primitives-written counter is reset to 0. Subsequent rendering will increment the counter once for every vertex that is written into the bound transform feedback buffer(s). If transform feedback mode is not activated between the call to glBeginQuery and glEndQuery, the counter will not be incremented. When glEndQuery is executed, the primitives-written counter is assigned to the query object's result value. This value can be queried by calling glGetQueryObject with pname GL_QUERY_RESULT.

If target is GL_TIME_ELAPSED, id must be an unused name, or the name of an existing timer query object previously bound to the GL_TIME_ELAPSED query binding. When glBeginQuery is executed, the query object's time counter is reset to 0. When glEndQuery is executed, the elapsed server time that has passed since the call to glBeginQuery is written into the query object's time counter. This value can be queried by calling glGetQueryObject with pname GL_QUERY_RESULT.

Querying the GL_QUERY_RESULT implicitly flushes the GL pipeline until the rendering delimited by the query object has completed and the result is available. GL_QUERY_RESULT_AVAILABLE can be queried to determine if the result is immediately available or if the rendering is not yet complete.

Notes

If the query target's count exceeds the maximum value representable in the number of available bits, as reported by glGetQueryiv with target set to the appropriate query target and pname GL_QUERY_COUNTER_BITS, the count becomes undefined.

An implementation may support 0 bits in its counter, in which case query results are always undefined and essentially useless.

When GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS is 0, the samples-passed counter of an occlusion query will increment once for each fragment that passes the depth test. When GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS is 1, an implementation may either increment the samples-passed counter individually for each sample of a fragment that passes the depth test, or it may choose to increment the counter for all samples of a fragment if any one of them passes the depth test.

The query targets GL_ANY_SAMPLES_PASSED, and GL_TIME_ELAPSED are availale only if the GL version is 3.3 or higher.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not one of the accepted tokens.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if glBeginQuery is executed while a query object of the same target is already active.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if glEndQuery is executed when a query object of the same target is not active.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if id is 0.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if id is the name of an already active query object.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if id refers to an existing query object whose type does not does not match target.

See Also

glDeleteQueries, glGenQueries, glGetQueryiv, glGetQueryObject, glIsQuery

Copyright

Copyright © 2005 Addison-Wesley. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBindFragDataLocation — bind a user-defined varying out variable to a fragment shader color number

C Specification

void glBindFragDataLocation( | GLuint program,
  | GLuint colorNumber,
  | const char * name);

Parameters

program

The name of the program containing varying out variable whose binding to modify

colorNumber

The color number to bind the user-defined varying out variable to

name

The name of the user-defined varying out variable whose binding to modify

Description

glBindFragDataLocation explicitly specifies the binding of the user-defined varying out variable name to fragment shader color number colorNumber for program program. If name was bound previously, its assigned binding is replaced with colorNumber. name must be a null-terminated string. colorNumber must be less than GL_MAX_DRAW_BUFFERS.

The bindings specified by glBindFragDataLocation have no effect until program is next linked. Bindings may be specified at any time after program has been created. Specifically, they may be specified before shader objects are attached to the program. Therefore, any name may be specified in name, including a name that is never used as a varying out variable in any fragment shader object. Names beginning with gl_ are reserved by the GL.

In addition to the errors generated by glBindFragDataLocation, the program program will fail to link if:

The number of active outputs is greater than the value GL_MAX_DRAW_BUFFERS.

More than one varying out variable is bound to the same color number.

Notes

Varying out varyings may have indexed locations assigned explicitly in the shader text using a location layout qualifier. If a shader statically assigns a location to a varying out variable in the shader text, that location is used and any location assigned with glBindFragDataLocation is ignored.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if colorNumber is greater than or equal to GL_MAX_DRAW_BUFFERS.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if name starts with the reserved gl_ prefix.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not the name of a program object.

Associated Gets

glGetFragDataLocation with a valid program object and the the name of a user-defined varying out variable

See Also

glCreateProgram, glGetFragDataLocation

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glBlitFramebuffer — copy a block of pixels from the read framebuffer to the draw framebuffer

C Specification

void glBlitFramebuffer( | GLint srcX0,
  | GLint srcY0,
  | GLint srcX1,
  | GLint srcY1,
  | GLint dstX0,
  | GLint dstY0,
  | GLint dstX1,
  | GLint dstY1,
  | GLbitfield mask,
  | GLenum filter);

Parameters

srcX0, srcY0, srcX1, srcY1

Specify the bounds of the source rectangle within the read buffer of the read framebuffer.

dstX0, dstY0, dstX1, dstY1

Specify the bounds of the destination rectangle within the write buffer of the write framebuffer.

mask

The bitwise OR of the flags indicating which buffers are to be copied. The allowed flags are GL_COLOR_BUFFER_BIT, GL_DEPTH_BUFFER_BIT and GL_STENCIL_BUFFER_BIT.

filter

Specifies the interpolation to be applied if the image is stretched. Must be GL_NEAREST or GL_LINEAR.

Description

glBlitFramebuffer transfers a rectangle of pixel values from one region of the read framebuffer to another region in the draw framebuffer. mask is the bitwise OR of a number of values indicating which buffers are to be copied. The values are GL_COLOR_BUFFER_BIT, GL_DEPTH_BUFFER_BIT, and GL_STENCIL_BUFFER_BIT. The pixels corresponding to these buffers are copied from the source rectangle bounded by the locations (srcX0; srcY0) and (srcX1; srcY1) to the destination rectangle bounded by the locations (dstX0; dstY0) and (dstX1; dstY1). The lower bounds of the rectangle are inclusive, while the upper bounds are exclusive.

The actual region taken from the read framebuffer is limited to the intersection of the source buffers being transferred, which may include the color buffer selected by the read buffer, the depth buffer, and/or the stencil buffer depending on mask. The actual region written to the draw framebuffer is limited to the intersection of the destination buffers being written, which may include multiple draw buffers, the depth buffer, and/or the stencil buffer depending on mask. Whether or not the source or destination regions are altered due to these limits, the scaling and offset applied to pixels being transferred is performed as though no such limits were present.

If the sizes of the source and destination rectangles are not equal, filter specifies the interpolation method that will be applied to resize the source image , and must be GL_NEAREST or GL_LINEAR. GL_LINEAR is only a valid interpolation method for the color buffer. If filter is not GL_NEAREST and mask includes GL_DEPTH_BUFFER_BIT or GL_STENCIL_BUFFER_BIT, no data is transferred and a GL_INVALID_OPERATION error is generated.

If filter is GL_LINEAR and the source rectangle would require sampling outside the bounds of the source framebuffer, values are read as if the GL_CLAMP_TO_EDGE texture wrapping mode were applied.

When the color buffer is transferred, values are taken from the read buffer of the read framebuffer and written to each of the draw buffers of the draw framebuffer.

If the source and destination rectangles overlap or are the same, and the read and draw buffers are the same, the result of the operation is undefined.

Errors

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if mask contains any of the GL_DEPTH_BUFFER_BIT or GL_STENCIL_BUFFER_BIT and filter is not GL_NEAREST.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if mask contains GL_COLOR_BUFFER_BIT and any of the following conditions hold:

The read buffer contains fixed-point or floating-point values and any draw buffer contains neither fixed-point nor floating-point values.

The read buffer contains unsigned integer values and any draw buffer does not contain unsigned integer values.

The read buffer contains signed integer values and any draw buffer does not contain signed integer values.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if mask contains GL_DEPTH_BUFFER_BIT or GL_STENCIL_BUFFER_BIT and the source and destination depth and stencil formats do not match.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if filter is GL_LINEAR and the read buffer contains integer data.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the value of GL_SAMPLES for the read and draw buffers is not identical.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if GL_SAMPLE_BUFFERS for both read and draw buffers greater than zero and the dimensions of the source and destination rectangles is not identical.

GL_INVALID_FRAMEBUFFER_OPERATION is generated if the objects bound to GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER_BINDING or GL_READ_FRAMEBUFFER_BINDING are not framebuffer complete.

See Also

glReadPixels glCheckFramebufferStatus, glGenFramebuffers glBindFramebuffer glDeleteFramebuffers

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glCheckFramebufferStatus — check the completeness status of a framebuffer

C Specification

GLenum glCheckFramebufferStatus( | GLenum target);

Parameters

target

Specify the target of the framebuffer completeness check.

Description

glCheckFramebufferStatus queries the completeness status of the framebuffer object currently bound to target. target must be GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER, GL_READ_FRAMEBUFFER or GL_FRAMEBUFFER. GL_FRAMEBUFFER is equivalent to GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER.

The return value is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_COMPLETE if the framebuffer bound to target is complete. Otherwise, the return value is determined as follows:

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_UNDEFINED is returned if target is the default framebuffer, but the default framebuffer does not exist.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_ATTACHMENT is returned if any of the framebuffer attachment points are framebuffer incomplete.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_MISSING_ATTACHMENT is returned if the framebuffer does not have at least one image attached to it.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_DRAW_BUFFER is returned if the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_NONE for any color attachment point(s) named by GL_DRAW_BUFFERi.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_READ_BUFFER is returned if GL_READ_BUFFER is not GL_NONE and the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_NONE for the color attachment point named by GL_READ_BUFFER.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_UNSUPPORTED is returned if the combination of internal formats of the attached images violates an implementation-dependent set of restrictions.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_MULTISAMPLE is returned if the value of GL_RENDERBUFFER_SAMPLES is not the same for all attached renderbuffers; if the value of GL_TEXTURE_SAMPLES is the not same for all attached textures; or, if the attached images are a mix of renderbuffers and textures, the value of GL_RENDERBUFFER_SAMPLES does not match the value of GL_TEXTURE_SAMPLES.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_MULTISAMPLE is also returned if the value of GL_TEXTURE_FIXED_SAMPLE_LOCATIONS is not the same for all attached textures; or, if the attached images are a mix of renderbuffers and textures, the value of GL_TEXTURE_FIXED_SAMPLE_LOCATIONS is not GL_TRUE for all attached textures.

GL_FRAMEBUFFER_INCOMPLETE_LAYER_TARGETS is returned if any framebuffer attachment is layered, and any populated attachment is not layered, or if all populated color attachments are not from textures of the same target.

Additionally, if an error occurs, zero is returned.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER, GL_READ_FRAMEBUFFER or GL_FRAMEBUFFER.

See Also

glGenFramebuffers, glDeleteFramebuffers glBindFramebuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glFramebufferRenderbuffer — attach a renderbuffer as a logical buffer to the currently bound framebuffer object

C Specification

void glFramebufferRenderbuffer( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum attachment,
  | GLenum renderbuffertarget,
  | GLuint renderbuffer);

Parameters

target

Specifies the framebuffer target. target must be GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER, GL_READ_FRAMEBUFFER, or GL_FRAMEBUFFER. GL_FRAMEBUFFER is equivalent to GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER.

attachment

Specifies the attachment point of the framebuffer.

renderbuffertarget

Specifies the renderbuffer target and must be GL_RENDERBUFFER.

renderbuffer

Specifies the name of an existing renderbuffer object of type renderbuffertarget to attach.

Description

glFramebufferRenderbuffer attaches a renderbuffer as one of the logical buffers of the currently bound framebuffer object. renderbuffer is the name of the renderbuffer object to attach and must be either zero, or the name of an existing renderbuffer object of type renderbuffertarget. If renderbuffer is not zero and if glFramebufferRenderbuffer is successful, then the renderbuffer name renderbuffer will be used as the logical buffer identified by attachment of the framebuffer currently bound to target.

The value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE for the specified attachment point is set to GL_RENDERBUFFER and the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is set to renderbuffer. All other state values of the attachment point specified by attachment are set to their default values. No change is made to the state of the renderbuuffer object and any previous attachment to the attachment logical buffer of the framebuffer target is broken.

Calling glFramebufferRenderbuffer with the renderbuffer name zero will detach the image, if any, identified by attachment, in the framebuffer currently bound to target. All state values of the attachment point specified by attachment in the object bound to target are set to their default values.

Setting attachment to the value GL_DEPTH_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT is a special case causing both the depth and stencil attachments of the framebuffer object to be set to renderbuffer, which should have the base internal format GL_DEPTH_STENCIL.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not one of the accepted tokens.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if renderbuffertarget is not GL_RENDERBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if zero is bound to target.

See Also

glGenFramebuffers, glBindFramebuffer, glGenRenderbuffers, glFramebufferTexture, glFramebufferTexture1D, glFramebufferTexture2D, glFramebufferTexture3D

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetActiveUniformBlock — query information about an active uniform block

C Specification

void glGetActiveUniformBlockiv( | GLuint program,
  | GLuint uniformBlockIndex,
  | GLenum pname,
  | GLint *params);

Parameters

program

Specifies the name of a program containing the uniform block.

uniformBlockIndex

Specifies the index of the uniform block within program.

pname

Specifies the name of the parameter to query.

params

Specifies the address of a variable to receive the result of the query.

Description

glGetActiveUniformBlockiv retrieves information about an active uniform block within program.

program must be the name of a program object for which the command glLinkProgram must have been called in the past, although it is not required that glLinkProgram must have succeeded. The link could have failed because the number of active uniforms exceeded the limit.

uniformBlockIndex is an active uniform block index of program, and must be less than the value of GL_ACTIVE_UNIFORM_BLOCKS.

Upon success, the uniform block parameter(s) specified by pname are returned in params. If an error occurs, nothing will be written to params.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_BINDING, then the index of the uniform buffer binding point last selected by the uniform block specified by uniformBlockIndex for program is returned. If no uniform block has been previously specified, zero is returned.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_DATA_SIZE, then the implementation-dependent minimum total buffer object size, in basic machine units, required to hold all active uniforms in the uniform block identified by uniformBlockIndex is returned. It is neither guaranteed nor expected that a given implementation will arrange uniform values as tightly packed in a buffer object. The exception to this is the std140 uniform block layout, which guarantees specific packing behavior and does not require the application to query for offsets and strides. In this case the minimum size may still be queried, even though it is determined in advance based only on the uniform block declaration.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_NAME_LENGTH, then the total length (including the nul terminator) of the name of the uniform block identified by uniformBlockIndex is returned.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_ACTIVE_UNIFORMS, then the number of active uniforms in the uniform block identified by uniformBlockIndex is returned.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_ACTIVE_UNIFORM_INDICES, then a list of the active uniform indices for the uniform block identified by uniformBlockIndex is returned. The number of elements that will be written to params is the value of GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_ACTIVE_UNIFORMS for uniformBlockIndex.

If pname is GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_REFERENCED_BY_VERTEX_SHADER, GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_REFERENCED_BY_GEOMETRY_SHADER, or GL_UNIFORM_BLOCK_REFERENCED_BY_FRAGMENT_SHADER, then a boolean value indicating whether the uniform block identified by uniformBlockIndex is referenced by the vertex, geometry, or fragment programming stages of program, respectively, is returned.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if uniformBlockIndex is greater than or equal to the value of GL_ACTIVE_UNIFORM_BLOCKS or is not the index of an active uniform block in program.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if pname is not one of the accepted tokens.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not the name of a program object for which glLinkProgram has been called in the past.

Notes

glGetActiveUniformBlockiv is available only if the GL version is 3.1 or greater.

See Also

glGetActiveUniformBlockName, glGetUniformBlockIndex, glLinkProgram

Copyright

Copyright © 2010-2013 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetError — return error information

C Specification

GLenum glGetError( void);

Description

glGetError returns the value of the error flag. Each detectable error is assigned a numeric code and symbolic name. When an error occurs, the error flag is set to the appropriate error code value. No other errors are recorded until glGetError is called, the error code is returned, and the flag is reset to GL_NO_ERROR. If a call to glGetError returns GL_NO_ERROR, there has been no detectable error since the last call to glGetError, or since the GL was initialized.

To allow for distributed implementations, there may be several error flags. If any single error flag has recorded an error, the value of that flag is returned and that flag is reset to GL_NO_ERROR when glGetError is called. If more than one flag has recorded an error, glGetError returns and clears an arbitrary error flag value. Thus, glGetError should always be called in a loop, until it returns GL_NO_ERROR, if all error flags are to be reset.

Initially, all error flags are set to GL_NO_ERROR.

The following errors are currently defined:

GL_NO_ERROR

No error has been recorded. The value of this symbolic constant is guaranteed to be 0.

GL_INVALID_ENUM

An unacceptable value is specified for an enumerated argument. The offending command is ignored and has no other side effect than to set the error flag.

GL_INVALID_VALUE

A numeric argument is out of range. The offending command is ignored and has no other side effect than to set the error flag.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION

The specified operation is not allowed in the current state. The offending command is ignored and has no other side effect than to set the error flag.

GL_INVALID_FRAMEBUFFER_OPERATION

The framebuffer object is not complete. The offending command is ignored and has no other side effect than to set the error flag.

GL_OUT_OF_MEMORY

There is not enough memory left to execute the command. The state of the GL is undefined, except for the state of the error flags, after this error is recorded.

When an error flag is set, results of a GL operation are undefined only if GL_OUT_OF_MEMORY has occurred. In all other cases, the command generating the error is ignored and has no effect on the GL state or frame buffer contents. If the generating command returns a value, it returns 0. If glGetError itself generates an error, it returns 0.

Copyright

Copyright © 1991-2006 Silicon Graphics, Inc. This document is licensed under the SGI Free Software B License. For details, see http://oss.sgi.com/projects/FreeB/.

Name

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv — retrieve information about attachments of a bound framebuffer object

C Specification

void glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv( | GLenum target,
  | GLenum attachment,
  | GLenum pname,
  | GLint *params);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target of the query operation.

attachment

Specifies the attachment within target

pname

Specifies the parameter of attachment to query.

params

Specifies the address of a variable receive the value of pname for attachment.

Description

glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv returns information about attachments of a bound framebuffer object. target specifies the framebuffer binding point and must be GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER, GL_READ_FRAMEBUFFER or GL_FRAMEBUFFER. GL_FRAMEBUFFER is equivalent to GL_DRAW_FRAMEBUFFER.

If the default framebuffer is bound to target then attachment must be one of GL_FRONT_LEFT, GL_FRONT_RIGHT, GL_BACK_LEFT, or GL_BACK_RIGHT, identifying a color buffer, GL_DEPTH, identifying the depth buffer, or GL_STENCIL, identifying the stencil buffer.

If a framebuffer object is bound, then attachment must be one of GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENTi, GL_DEPTH_ATTACHMENT, GL_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT, or GL_DEPTH_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT. i in GL_COLOR_ATTACHMENTi must be in the range zero to the value of GL_MAX_COLOR_ATTACHMENTS - 1.

If attachment is GL_DEPTH_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT and different objects are bound to the depth and stencil attachment points of target the query will fail. If the same object is bound to both attachment points, information about that object will be returned.

Upon successful return from glGetFramebufferAttachmentParameteriv, if pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE, then params will contain one of GL_NONE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_DEFAULT, GL_TEXTURE, or GL_RENDERBUFFER, identifying the type of object which contains the attached image. Other values accepted for pname depend on the type of object, as described below.

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_NONE, no framebuffer is bound to target. In this case querying pname GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME will return zero, and all other queries will generate an error.

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is not GL_NONE, these queries apply to all other framebuffer types:

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_RED_SIZE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_GREEN_SIZE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_BLUE_SIZE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_ALPHA_SIZE, GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_DEPTH_SIZE, or GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_STENCIL_SIZE, then params will contain the number of bits in the corresponding red, green, blue, alpha, depth, or stencil component of the specified attachment. Zero is returned if the requested component is not present in attachment.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_COMPONENT_TYPE, params will contain the format of components of the specified attachment, one of GL_FLOAT, GL_INT, GL_UNSIGNED_INT, GL_SIGNED_NORMALIZED, or GL_UNSIGNED_NORMALIZED for floating-point, signed integer, unsigned integer, signed normalized fixed-point, or unsigned normalized fixed-point components respectively. Only color buffers may have integer components.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_COLOR_ENCODING, param will contain the encoding of components of the specified attachment, one of GL_LINEAR or GL_SRGB for linear or sRGB-encoded components, respectively. Only color buffer components may be sRGB-encoded; such components are treated as described in sections 4.1.7 and 4.1.8. For the default framebuffer, color encoding is determined by the implementation. For framebuffer objects, components are sRGB-encoded if the internal format of a color attachment is one of the color-renderable SRGB formats.

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_RENDERBUFFER, then:

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME, params will contain the name of the renderbuffer object which contains the attached image.

If the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_TEXTURE, then:

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME, then params will contain the name of the texture object which contains the attached image.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LEVEL, then params will contain the mipmap level of the texture object which contains the attached image.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_FACE and the texture object named GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is a cube map texture, then params will contain the cube map face of the cubemap texture object which contains the attached image. Otherwise params will contain the value zero.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_TEXTURE_LAYER and the texture object named GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME is a layer of a three-dimensional texture or a one-or two-dimensional array texture, then params will contain the number of the texture layer which contains the attached image. Otherwise params will contain the value zero.

If pname is GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_LAYERED, then params will contain GL_TRUE if an entire level of a three-dimesional texture, cube map texture, or one-or two-dimensional array texture is attached. Otherwise, params will contain GL_FALSE.

Any combinations of framebuffer type and pname not described above will generate an error.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not one of the accepted tokens.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if pname is not valid for the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if attachment is not the accepted values for target.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if attachment is GL_DEPTH_STENCIL_ATTACHMENT and different objects are bound to the depth and stencil attachment points of target.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if the value of GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_TYPE is GL_NONE and pname is not GL_FRAMEBUFFER_ATTACHMENT_OBJECT_NAME.

See Also

glGenFramebuffers, glBindFramebuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2010-2013 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glGetUniform — Returns the value of a uniform variable

C Specification

void glGetUniformfv( | GLuint   | program,
  | GLint   | location,
  | GLfloat *  | params);

void glGetUniformiv( | GLuint   | program,
  | GLint   | location,
  | GLint *  | params);

void glGetUniformuiv( | GLuint   | program,
  | GLint   | location,
  | GLuint *  | params);

Parameters

program

Specifies the program object to be queried.

location

Specifies the location of the uniform variable to be queried.

params

Returns the value of the specified uniform variable.

Description

glGetUniform returns in params the value(s) of the specified uniform variable. The type of the uniform variable specified by location determines the number of values returned. If the uniform variable is defined in the shader as a boolean, int, or float, a single value will be returned. If it is defined as a vec2, ivec2, or bvec2, two values will be returned. If it is defined as a vec3, ivec3, or bvec3, three values will be returned, and so on. To query values stored in uniform variables declared as arrays, call glGetUniform for each element of the array. To query values stored in uniform variables declared as structures, call glGetUniform for each field in the structure. The values for uniform variables declared as a matrix will be returned in column major order.

The locations assigned to uniform variables are not known until the program object is linked. After linking has occurred, the command glGetUniformLocation can be used to obtain the location of a uniform variable. This location value can then be passed to glGetUniform in order to query the current value of the uniform variable. After a program object has been linked successfully, the index values for uniform variables remain fixed until the next link command occurs. The uniform variable values can only be queried after a link if the link was successful.

Notes

If an error is generated, no change is made to the contents of params.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if program is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not a program object.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program has not been successfully linked.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if location does not correspond to a valid uniform variable location for the specified program object.

Associated Gets

glGetActiveUniform with arguments program and the index of an active uniform variable

glGetProgram with arguments program and GL_ACTIVE_UNIFORMS or GL_ACTIVE_UNIFORM_MAX_LENGTH

glGetUniformLocation with arguments program and the name of a uniform variable

glIsProgram

See Also

glCreateProgram, glLinkProgram, glUniform

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glMapBufferRange — map a section of a buffer object's data store

C Specification

void *glMapBufferRange( | GLenum target,
  | GLintptr offset,
  | GLsizeiptr length,
  | GLbitfield access);

Parameters

target

Specifies a binding to which the target buffer is bound.

offset

Specifies a the starting offset within the buffer of the range to be mapped.

length

Specifies a length of the range to be mapped.

access

Specifies a combination of access flags indicating the desired access to the range.

Description

glMapBufferRange maps all or part of the data store of a buffer object into the client's address space. target specifies the target to which the buffer is bound and must be one of GL_ARRAY_BUFFER, GL_COPY_READ_BUFFER, GL_COPY_WRITE_BUFFER, GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER, GL_PIXEL_PACK_BUFFER, GL_PIXEL_UNPACK_BUFFER, GL_TEXTURE_BUFFER, GL_TRANSFORM_FEEDBACK_BUFFER, or GL_UNIFORM_BUFFER. offset and length indicate the range of data in the buffer object htat is to be mapped, in terms of basic machine units. access is a bitfield containing flags which describe the requested mapping. These flags are described below.

If no error occurs, a pointer to the beginning of the mapped range is returned once all pending operations on that buffer have completed, and may be used to modify and/or query the corresponding range of the buffer, according to the following flag bits set in access:

GL_MAP_READ_BIT indicates that the returned pointer may be used to read buffer object data. No GL error is generated if the pointer is used to query a mapping which excludes this flag, but the result is undefined and system errors (possibly including program termination) may occur.

GL_MAP_WRITE_BIT indicates that the returned pointer may be used to modify buffer object data. No GL error is generated if the pointer is used to modify a mapping which excludes this flag, but the result is undefined and system errors (possibly including program termination) may occur.

Furthermore, the following optional flag bits in access may be used to modify the mapping:

GL_MAP_INVALIDATE_RANGE_BIT indicates that the previous contents of the specified range may be discarded. Data within this range are undefined with the exception of subsequently written data. No GL error is generated if sub- sequent GL operations access unwritten data, but the result is undefined and system errors (possibly including program termination) may occur. This flag may not be used in combination with GL_MAP_READ_BIT.

GL_MAP_INVALIDATE_BUFFER_BIT indicates that the previous contents of the entire buffer may be discarded. Data within the entire buffer are undefined with the exception of subsequently written data. No GL error is generated if subsequent GL operations access unwritten data, but the result is undefined and system errors (possibly including program termination) may occur. This flag may not be used in combination with GL_MAP_READ_BIT.

GL_MAP_FLUSH_EXPLICIT_BIT indicates that one or more discrete subranges of the mapping may be modified. When this flag is set, modifications to each subrange must be explicitly flushed by calling glFlushMappedBufferRange. No GL error is set if a subrange of the mapping is modified and not flushed, but data within the corresponding subrange of the buffer are undefined. This flag may only be used in conjunction with GL_MAP_WRITE_BIT. When this option is selected, flushing is strictly limited to regions that are explicitly indicated with calls to glFlushMappedBufferRange prior to unmap; if this option is not selected glUnmapBuffer will automatically flush the entire mapped range when called.

GL_MAP_UNSYNCHRONIZED_BIT indicates that the GL should not attempt to synchronize pending operations on the buffer prior to returning from glMapBufferRange. No GL error is generated if pending operations which source or modify the buffer overlap the mapped region, but the result of such previous and any subsequent operations is undefined.

If an error occurs, glMapBufferRange returns a NULL pointer.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if either of offset or length is negative, or if offset + length is greater than the value of GL_BUFFER_SIZE.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if access has any bits set other than those defined above.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated for any of the following conditions:

The buffer is already in a mapped state.

Neither GL_MAP_READ_BIT or GL_MAP_WRITE_BIT is set.

GL_MAP_READ_BIT is set and any of GL_MAP_INVALIDATE_RANGE_BIT, GL_MAP_INVALIDATE_BUFFER_BIT, or GL_MAP_UNSYNCHRONIZED_BIT is set.

GL_MAP_FLUSH_EXPLICIT_BIT is set and GL_MAP_WRITE_BIT is not set.

GL_OUT_OF_MEMORY is generated if glMapBufferRange fails because memory for the mapping could not be obtained.

See Also

glMapBuffer, glFlushMappedBufferRange, glBindBuffer

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glRenderbufferStorageMultisample — establish data storage, format, dimensions and sample count of a renderbuffer object's image

C Specification

void glRenderbufferStorageMultisample( | GLenum target,
  | GLsizei samples,
  | GLenum internalformat,
  | GLsizei width,
  | GLsizei height);

Parameters

target

Specifies a binding to which the target of the allocation and must be GL_RENDERBUFFER.

samples

Specifies the number of samples to be used for the renderbuffer object's storage.

internalformat

Specifies the internal format to use for the renderbuffer object's image.

width

Specifies the width of the renderbuffer, in pixels.

height

Specifies the height of the renderbuffer, in pixels.

Description

glRenderbufferStorageMultisample establishes the data storage, format, dimensions and number of samples of a renderbuffer object's image.

The target of the operation, specified by target must be GL_RENDERBUFFER. internalformat specifies the internal format to be used for the renderbuffer object's storage and must be a color-renderable, depth-renderable, or stencil-renderable format. width and height are the dimensions, in pixels, of the renderbuffer. Both width and height must be less than or equal to the value of GL_MAX_RENDERBUFFER_SIZE. samples specifies the number of samples to be used for the renderbuffer object's image, and must be less than or equal to the value of GL_MAX_SAMPLES. If internalformat is a signed or unsigned integer format then samples must be less than or equal to the value of GL_MAX_INTEGER_SAMPLES.

Upon success, glRenderbufferStorageMultisample deletes any existing data store for the renderbuffer image and the contents of the data store after calling glRenderbufferStorageMultisample are undefined.

Errors

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if target is not GL_RENDERBUFFER.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if samples is greater than GL_MAX_SAMPLES.

GL_INVALID_ENUM is generated if internalformat is not a color-renderable, depth-renderable, or stencil-renderable format.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if internalformat is a signed or unsigned integer format and samples is greater than the value of GL_MAX_INTEGER_SAMPLES

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if either of width or height is negative, or greater than the value of GL_MAX_RENDERBUFFER_SIZE.

GL_OUT_OF_MEMORY is generated if the GL is unable to create a data store of the requested size.

See Also

glGenRenderbuffers, glBindRenderbuffer, glRenderbufferStorage, glFramebufferRenderbuffer, glDeleteRenderbuffers

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glTexImage3DMultisample — establish the data storage, format, dimensions, and number of samples of a multisample texture's image

C Specification

void glTexImage3DMultisample( | GLenum target,
  | GLsizei samples,
  | GLint internalformat,
  | GLsizei width,
  | GLsizei height,
  | GLsizei depth,
  | GLboolean fixedsamplelocations);

Parameters

target

Specifies the target of the operation. target must be GL_TEXTURE_2D_MULTISAMPLE_ARRAY or GL_PROXY_TEXTURE_2D_MULTISAMPLE_ARRAY.

samples

The number of samples in the multisample texture's image.

internalformat

The internal format to be used to store the multisample texture's image. internalformat must specify a color-renderable, depth-renderable, or stencil-renderable format.

width

The width of the multisample texture's image, in texels.

height

The height of the multisample texture's image, in texels.

fixedsamplelocations

Specifies whether the image will use identical sample locations and the same number of samples for all texels in the image, and the sample locations will not depend on the internal format or size of the image.

Description

glTexImage3DMultisample establishes the data storage, format, dimensions and number of samples of a multisample texture's image.

target must be GL_TEXTURE_2D_MULTISAMPLE_ARRAY or GL_PROXY_TEXTURE_2D_MULTISAMPLE_ARRAY. width and heightare the dimensions in texels of the texture, and must be in the range zero to GL_MAX_TEXTURE_SIZE - 1. depth is the number of array slices in the array texture's image. samples specifies the number of samples in the image and must be in the range zero to GL_MAX_SAMPLES - 1.

internalformat must be a color-renderable, depth-renderable, or stencil-renderable format.

If fixedsamplelocations is GL_TRUE, the image will use identical sample locations and the same number of samples for all texels in the image, and the sample locations will not depend on the internal format or size of the image.

When a multisample texture is accessed in a shader, the access takes one vector of integers describing which texel to fetch and an integer corresponding to the sample numbers describing which sample within the texel to fetch. No standard sampling instructions are allowed on the multisample texture targets.

Notes

glTexImage2DMultisample is available only if the GL version is 3.2 or greater.

Errors

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if internalformat is a depth- or stencil-renderable format and samples is greater than the value of GL_MAX_DEPTH_TEXTURE_SAMPLES.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if internalformat is a color-renderable format and samples is greater than the value of GL_MAX_COLOR_TEXTURE_SAMPLES.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if internalformat is a signed or unsigned integer format and samples is greater than the value of GL_MAX_INTEGER_SAMPLES.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if either width or height negative or is greater than GL_MAX_TEXTURE_SIZE.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if depth is negative or is greater than GL_MAX_ARRAY_TEXTURE_LAYERS.

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if samples is greater than GL_MAX_SAMPLES.

See Also

glTexImage3D, glTexImage2DMultisample

Copyright

Copyright © 2010 Khronos Group. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.

Name

glValidateProgram — Validates a program object

C Specification

void glValidateProgram( | GLuint program);

Parameters

program

Specifies the handle of the program object to be validated.

Description

glValidateProgram checks to see whether the executables contained in program can execute given the current OpenGL state. The information generated by the validation process will be stored in program's information log. The validation information may consist of an empty string, or it may be a string containing information about how the current program object interacts with the rest of current OpenGL state. This provides a way for OpenGL implementers to convey more information about why the current program is inefficient, suboptimal, failing to execute, and so on.

The status of the validation operation will be stored as part of the program object's state. This value will be set to GL_TRUE if the validation succeeded, and GL_FALSE otherwise. It can be queried by calling glGetProgram with arguments program and GL_VALIDATE_STATUS. If validation is successful, program is guaranteed to execute given the current state. Otherwise, program is guaranteed to not execute.

This function is typically useful only during application development. The informational string stored in the information log is completely implementation dependent; therefore, an application should not expect different OpenGL implementations to produce identical information strings.

Notes

This function mimics the validation operation that OpenGL implementations must perform when rendering commands are issued while programmable shaders are part of current state. The error GL_INVALID_OPERATION will be generated by any command that triggers the rendering of geometry if:

any two active samplers in the current program object are of different types, but refer to the same texture image unit,

the number of active samplers in the program exceeds the maximum number of texture image units allowed.

It may be difficult or cause a performance degradation for applications to catch these errors when rendering commands are issued. Therefore, applications are advised to make calls to glValidateProgram to detect these issues during application development.

Errors

GL_INVALID_VALUE is generated if program is not a value generated by OpenGL.

GL_INVALID_OPERATION is generated if program is not a program object.

Associated Gets

glGetProgram with arguments program and GL_VALIDATE_STATUS

glGetProgramInfoLog with argument program

glIsProgram

See Also

glLinkProgram, glUseProgram

Copyright

Copyright © 2003-2005 3Dlabs Inc. Ltd. This material may be distributed subject to the terms and conditions set forth in the Open Publication License, v 1.0, 8 June 1999. http://opencontent.org/openpub/.